Guide to the Warner D. Miller Collection, [ca. 1930-1945].
Miller, Warner D. Collection, [ca. 1930-1945]
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Warner D. Miller Collection, [ca. 1930-1945].
9180
Warner D, Miller
2 cubic ft.
Correspondence, Diaries, Photographs, Research Materials
Division of Rare and Manuscript Collections, Cornell University Library
Notebooks, sketches, postcards, photographs, manuscripts, Indian vocabularies, poetry, newspaper clippings, and maps. Most pertaining to mid west and northern Great Plains Indians. There are many sketches of native plants, some of them appear to have been copied from botanical books, but others appear to be original drawings also sketches of land formations. Biographic and encyclopedic information on Indians and their customs. Notes regarding places of the west he visited, cowboys, how to tie knots on the range, Indian name origins, games. A focus on Indian legends, fables, and folklore. Maps and information on South and North Dakota.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
Warner D. Miller was an amateur ethnographer, and artist. He also was a teacher on the Standing Rock, Cheyenne, and Rosebud Reservations in the first part of the twentieth century. Almost immediately, he began to record the stories he heard and events he witnessed. He was also an amateur artist, and often illustrated the legends he recounted.
COLLECTION DESCRIPTION
Notebooks, sketches, postcards, photographs, manuscripts, Indian vocabularies, poetry, newspaper clippings, and maps. Most pertaining to mid west and northern Great Plains Indians. There are many sketches of native plants, some of them appear to have been copied from botanical books, but others appear to be original drawings also sketches of land formations. Biographic and encyclopedic information on Indians and their customs. Notes regarding places of the west he visited, cowboys, how to tie knots on the range, Indian name origins, games. A focus on Indian legends, fables, and folklore. Maps and information on South and North Dakota.
Also, CD containing digital photographs of the entire collection.
SUBJECTS
Names:
Miller, Warner D,; Biddle, Nicholas 1786-1844.; Catlin, George, 1796-1872.; Glass, Hugh, ca. 1780-ca. 1833.; Mouse, Tom White.; Habberstad, Helen M.; Huntington Free Library.; United States.Bureau of Indian Affairs.Standing Rock Agency.; Lewis and Clark Expedition
Subjects:
Indians of North America.; Indians of North America; Indians of North America; Indians of North America--Education.; Indians of North America; Indians of North America--Games.; Indians of North America--Jewelry.; Indians of North America--Languages.; Indian sign language.; Knots and splices.; Sun dance.; Dakota Indians.; Winnebago Indians.
Places:
Eagle Nest Butte.; Iowa River (Iowa); Lac qui Parle River (Minn.); Mde Iyedan.; Medicine Butte.; Mississippi River.; Pipestone Indian Reservation (Minn.); Red Butte.; Standing Rock Indian Reservation (N.D. and S.D.); Thunder Butte.; White River (S.D.)
Form and Genre Terms:
Maps.; Paintings.; Photographs.; Postcards.
INFORMATION FOR USERS
The Warner D. Miller papers offer a great opportunity to learn about the Native Americans living on the Standing Rock and Rosebud Reservations in the Great Plains during the first half of the twentieth century. Miller was a teacher on the Standing Rock, Cheyenne, and Rosebud Reservations in the first part of the twentieth century. Almost immediately, he began to record the stories he heard and events he witnessed. He was also an amateur artist, and often illustrated the legends he recounted.
Information gleaned from the collection indicates that Warner D. Miller was born around 1890 in Maywood, Illinois. When he enlisted in the Army in 1918, he was living in Ida Grove, Iowa. He identifies himself as a telephone linesman and farmer at that time. Sometime after a 1919 honorable discharge from military service, he moved to South Dakota. He was teaching on the Standing Rock Reservation in 1927.
Miller was an amateur ethnographer, and artist. Some of the journals and papers in this collection recount the stories told to him by his students and other Native residents of the area. Sketches or drawings accompany many of the stories, some by his students, others by him. In an era when most ethnographers failed to identify their informants, Miller gave credit to his. Not only did he record their names, but also the town and/or reservation where they lived.
Miller's interest in Native Americans was not limited to South Dakota. His papers include several maps, many copied from published works, from all over the Midwest. In one case, he maps the location of an Indian village in Ida Grove, Iowa. According to Miller, it was abandoned in the 1850s.
"Knots of the Range," written by Miller, calling himself "Plainsman", was published as a series for juveniles in 1945 in The Christian Science Monitor. As the name implies, the articles offered instructions on how to make Western knots of every conceivable kind and use, knowledge he had obtained from the cowboys and Indians of the Great Plains. This file is quite extensive and contains sketches, drawings and copies of the final articles published. While much of the material in Miller's collection looks as if it were prepared for publication, "Knots" is the only actual publication the library has located.
Another interesting aspect of this collection is Miller's obvious fascination with the geography of the area. He has countless sketches of land formations. Of Medicine Butte, South Dakota, he writes: "Standing on the high flat at Oacoma scanning, Meriwether Lewis saw far to the northwest what appeared to be a long range of hills extending for some distance across the plains. What he really beheld were the lofty points of Medicine Butte."
Miller's fondness for the flora and fauna of the area is also evident in his papers. There are many sketches of native plants, some of them appear to have been copied from botanical books, but others appear to be original drawings. Because of the eclectic nature of these papers, to find every individual mentioned or legend recounted, his notes must be examined in depth.
CONTAINER LIST
- Collection overview and printed guide (Box 1, Folder 0)
- American Indian Sign Language (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Battle Hill, by W. D. Miller (Box 1, Folder 2)
- The Battle on the Ta' H Do Hu, by W. D. Miller (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Manuscript with photographs.
- Beading instructions (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Biddle accounts (Box 1, Folder 5)
- The Boundary Line by Warner Miller (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Biographical Notes (Box 1, Folder 7-10)
  - Misc. Biographical Notes (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Vocabulary, Sketches, stories and their Indian sources-misc. biographical notes and historical notes (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Teaching in the Indian Country, by W.D. Miller (Standing Rock Reservation, Bullhead, SD) (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Teaching in the Indian Country (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Catlin on Turning the Toes In. A page from history showing the injustice of war. Winnebago Calendar. An Indians Interpretation of the Twenty-third Psalm. (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Cattle (Box 1, Folder 12)
- A copy of a sketch by Mrs. Tom White Mouse (Mary Medicine Bear) Wood, South Dakota, 1943 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Drawings and Sketches (Box 1, Folder 14-19)
  - Drawing by Andrew Jacob, Ida Grove, IA., 1938 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    Also some notes by perhaps by Jacob.
  - Misc. Notes and Sketches (Box 1, Folder 15)
    10 pages.
  - Drawing by Nelson Stranger Horse (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Notes, Sketches and Maps (Box 1, Folder 17)
    23 pages.
  - Drawings of leaves (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sketches by Miller (Box 1, Folder 19)
- Mississippi River shore lines in South Dakota-following Lewis and Clarks notes and maps and adding maps and notes of his own (Box 1, Folder 20-23)
- Historic notes regarding the present city of Ida Grove, Iowa, by W.D. Miller (Box 1, Folder 24-26)
  Includes map of Early Sioux Village
- Journals with Notes, Sketches, Maps, Vocabulary, etc., by W.D. Miller (Box 1, Folder 27)
  16 journals.
- Indian Calendars (Box 1, Folder 28)
- An Indian Marble Game (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Indian Names Origin (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Knots of the Range newspaper article by Miller, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 31-35)
  Includes sketches and studies of knots (used for livestock and horses) to be used in newspaper articles.
- Indian Legends (Box 1, Folder 36-42)
  Includes drawings and sketches incorporated with the legends.
  - The Spirit of Turtle Head Knoll (Box 1, Folder 36)
    41 pages.
  - The Legend of Red Butte (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Legend of Rattlesnake Butte (Box 1, Folder 38)
    13 pages.
  - Legend of Thunder Butte (Box 1, Folder 38)
    5 pages.
  - Legend of Medicine Butte (Box 1, Folder 38)
    8 pages.
  - Indian legends and historical stories by Warner D. Miller with illustrations by the author, 1934-1935 (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Personal notes, legends, sketches, glossary of Indian tribes and misc. notes. (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - Legend of the Red Pipestone Quarry. (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - Legend of the Red Pipestone Quarry by Wa ya ru ge and Chief Red Thunder. (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Legends Duplicates (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Legends ledger with misc. notes and sketches by W.D. Miller (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Legends (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Notes regarding Indian legends by W.D. Miller (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - The story of Mde Iyedan and how Lac Quil Parle received its name by W. D. Miller (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Legends of Eagle Nest Butte, Hidden Timber (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Stories about: Buffalo Cliff; Hugh Glass (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - How a little Coyote showed his friendship, Dakota (Ogalala) told by Chief of the Oglala Sioux, American Horse, Pine Ridge Reservation, South Dakota. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - The Legend of Thunder Butte by Zintkala win Bird Woman (Mrs. Belle Pretty Boy), Rosebud Reservation, Norris, South Dakota. (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Indian legends by various people. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Indian fables by W.D. Miller. (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Fables from various Indian tribes. (Box 2, Folder 12)
- A letter containing Indian history of Sioux and Winnebagos, from Leo C. Conn (Box 2, Folder 13)
- Letter from Mildred Brave Crow. Sketches from John Winter and Lowell Spotted Elk (all Indian students of W. D. Miller.) (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Maps of some of South Dakotas rivers and islands. (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Iowa map (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Misc. notes, maps, etc. (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Sketches, notes and maps from South Dakota (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Tracing the course of the Iowa River: Ockeyedan-The Lookout of Iowa: The Farmer who had his Ups and Downs (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Maps. (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Misc. notes (Box 2, Folder 21)
  116 pages.
- Misc. papers. (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Misc. notes, maps, drawings (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Misc. notes and newspaper articles. (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Newspaper articles regarding Wood and So. White River Ancient Villages. (Box 2, Folder 25)
- North Dakota map (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Notes (includes name origin of Rosebud Reservation.) Explanation of various species of snakes. (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Owotanna (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Photographs and postcards (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Poetry by W. D. Miller (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Relics from the Dakota Diamond Jubilee, Yankton, South Dakota, June 7-13, 1936 (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Selected Quotations, and misc. notes (Box 2, Folder 32)
- A short sketch of the White River Country of S. Dakota by W. D. Miller (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Storm Lake (Box 2, Folder 34)
- The Sun Dance by Tom White Mouse, Wood, South Dakota: How to make a Sun Dial (Box 2, Folder 35)
- Tourist Information regarding U.S. Highway 16 in South Dakota (Box 2, Folder 36)
- A true likeness of War Eagle (Box 2, Folder 37)
- Where an Indian Trail once crossed the Maple River by W. D. Miller (Box 2, Folder 38)
- Woods, South Dakota (Box 2, Folder 39)
- Indian Vocabularies (and their sources) from many important tribes of the U.S. and Canada by Plainsman (Box 2, Folder 40-42)
- 2 CD's containing digital photos of entire collection (CD-2017 & 2018) (Box 2, Folder 43)